Guide to the Ernest and Olivia Ikenberry Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Ernest and Olivia Ikenberry Papers
1921-2005
RG 168
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(7 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the Ikenberrys' work in China and the U.S. Ernest and Olivia Ikenberry were American missionaries in China from 1922-1951, serving under the Church of the Brethren. Following their return from China they served at a Church of the Brethren mission among the Navajo Indians in Lybrook, New Mexico.
Ikenberry, Ernest, 1892-1974
Ikenberry, Olivia, 1896-1964
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of O. Susan Ikenberry Wilson, Ernest Ikenberry, Jr.
Biographical / Historical
1892 Ernest LeRoy Ikenberry born.
1920 B.A. McPherson College
1917 Installed as minister, McPherson Church of the Brethren
1922 Married Olivia Dickens, went to China
1922-1923 Language study in Peking
1923-1924 Stationed in Ping Ting, Shansi
1924-34 Tai Yuan, youth work with YMCA, on loan from Church of the Brethren
1927 Evacuated due to political unrest
1929 Graduated, Yale Divinity School; Returned to YMCA work in Tai Yuan
1934-40 Evangelistic work in Ping Ting
1937-40 Children at North China American School
1941 Returned to U.S.
1941-43 Pastor, Twin Falls, Idaho
1945 Ernest returned to Shanghai, China followed by Olivia in 1946
1945-48 National Christian Council of China and the China Office of Church World Service
1948-51 Church of the Brethren Mission Office, Shanghai
1951 Returned to USA
1951-53 Personnel Secretary for Brethren Mission Board, Elgin, Illinois
1954-1957 Re-opened Navajo Indian Mission in Lybrook, New Mexico
1958 Pastor, Brethren Church in Phoenix, Arizona
1962 Pastor, Aline, Oklahoma
1964 Wife Olivia died, Married Marguerite Berkey, former missionary to China and Japan
1964 Moved to LaVerne, California
1974 Died
1896 Olivia Dickens Ikenberry born
1915-17 Northfield Seminary
1917-19 Oberlin College
1919-21 McPherson College
1921-22 Taught at Daleville College
1922 Married Ernest Ikenberry, Went to China
1922 Went to China, taught in mission schools, worked with Chinese women
1944-46 Dean of Women, McPherson College
1946 Returned to China
1946-50 National Christian Council, Secretary, Women's Work; publicity writer: Church World Service
1964 Died
Scope and Contents
This record group contains relatively little material related to the Ikenberrys' work in China prior to their last stint in Shanghai following the second World War. Three times in their lives as missionaries in China, Olivia and Ernest Ikenberry had to evacuate because of dangerous war situations. First in 1927 when they were living in Tai Yuan, the warlords began fighting for power in Shansi. The second time, in the winter of 1940, they had been living under Japanese occupation for three years in Ping Ting, Shansi. At this time the Ikenberrys burned all their letters, papers, and accounts to keep them out of the hands of the Japanese, afraid that some information could be used against the Chinese Christians. This collection does contain circular letters, writings, and photographs documenting the Ikenberrys' work in China as well as correspondence and other materials related to their work among Native Americans in the U.S.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1921-1966
II. Sermons and Writings, 1921-1966
III. Collected Materials
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1922-2005
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Ikenberry, Ernest, 1892-1974; Ikenberry, Olivia, 1896-1964; Church of the Brethren -- Missions -- China
- Correspondence, 1921-1966; Series I
  - Family: Parents to Children, 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Addendum to family correspondence: Parents to children and extended family, 1936, 1938, 1946-1958 (Box 7, Folder 1-15)
  - General, Business, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lybrook Reports, 1953-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Support Newsletters, 1921-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Support newsletter to "Dear Friends" from Tai Yuan, Shansi, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with National Council of Churches and Yale Divinity School re. China Records Project, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Sermons and Writings, 1921-1966; Series II
  - ELI Sermons and Writings (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - ODI Publicity for Church World Service, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - ODI Writings re: China (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - ODI Writings re: Brethren (general) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - ODI Sermon Notes and Thesis (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sermons and Writings by others (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Christian Faith and Politics" by Y.T. Wu, ca. 1933 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Szechwan Cross Stitch Patterns" by Irma Highbaugh, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Typed notes for sermons and talks, 1958-1968 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Collected Materials, Series III
  - From China; Music, Reading books (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - About China (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - China Workshop (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Women's Work, National Christian Council, Shanghai (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Chinese Music, hymn book in Chinese/English (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Prayer (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Indian Affairs (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1922-2005; Series IV
  - Photographs, prior to China (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Photographs, from China (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Photographs, in USA prior to Lybrook (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Photographs, from Lybrook (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Photograph album, covering period from their marriage through trip across U.S. and first scenes in Peking. Identifications provided by daughter O. Susan Ikenberry Wilson., 1922 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photograph album, mostly family photos with some other missionaries, Chinese Christians, and scenes in Peking. Identifications provided by daughter., 1922-1934 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photograph album, from Tai Yuan years - missionaries, Chinese Christians, scenes. Identifications provided by daughter, 1928-1933 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Two mounted photographs of ELI with groups: Taiyuan YMCA English Evening School, YMCA Shansi University, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Lake Geneva School of Missions Scrapbook, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Memorablilia: trip from China to USA, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - ODI Bible and Notebook (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Navajo Gospel Hymns (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - McPherson Achievment Award and photos, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - ODI Biographical Papers; typescript material from donors re. lives and work of the Ikenberrys (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - ELI Biographical Papers (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Biographical material, including sketch of ELI and ODI by Susan Ikenberry Wilson (daughter), ca. 2005 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Interview with ELI, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Yale University Diploma, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 35)